Chapter 13. Wheelbarrow.
Next morning, Monday, after disposing of the embalmed head to a barber for a
block, I settled my own and comrades bill using, however, my comrades money.
The grinning landlord, as well as the borders, seemed amazingly tickled at the
sudden friendship which had sprung up between me and Quiqu, especially as
Peter Coffin's and bull stories about him had previously so much alarmed
me concerning the very person whom I now accompanied with. We borrowed a
wheelbarrow and embarking our things, including my own poor carpet bag and
Quiquake's canvas sack and hammock, a way went down to the moss. A little
Nantucket packet schooner mored at the wararf. As we were going along, the
people stared, not at Quequake so much, for they were used to seeing cannibals
like him in their streets, but at seeing him and me on such confidential terms.
But we heated them not, going along, wheeling the barrerow by turns, and
Quiquake now and then stopping to adjust the sheath on his harpoon barbs. I asked
him why he carried such a troublesome thing with him ashore, and whether all
whailing ships did not find their own harpoons. To this in substance he
replied that though what I hinted was true enough yet he had a particular
affection for his own harpoon because it was of assured stuff well tried in many
immortal combat and deeply intimate with the hearts of whales. In short like many
inland reapers and mowers who go into the farmers meadows armed with their own
sides though in no wise obliged to furnish them. Even so, Quiquake, for his
own private reasons, preferred his own harpoon.
Shifting the barrerow from my hand to his, he told me a funny story about the
first wheelbarrow he had ever seen. It was in Sag Harbor. The owners of his
ship, it seems, had lent him one, in which to carry his heavy chest to his
boarding house. Not to seem ignorant about the thing, though in truth he was
entirely so, concerning the precise way in which to manage the barrerow. Quiqu
put his chest upon it, lashes it fast, and then shoulders the barrerow and
marches up the warf. Why, said I, Quiqu, you might have known better than that,
one would think. Didn't the people laugh? Upon this he told me another
story. The people of his island of Kokavokco, it seems, at their wedding
feasts, express the fragrant water of young coconuts into a large stained
calabage like a punchbowl. And this punchbowl always forms the great central
ornament on the braided mat where the feast is held. Now, a certain grand
merchant ship once touched at Kokavokco, and its commander, uh, from all accounts
a very stately, punctilious gentleman, at least for a sea captain. This
commander was invited to the wedding feast of Quiquake's sister, a pretty
young princess just turned of 10. Well, when all the wedding guests were
assembled at the bride's bamboo cottage, this captain marches in, and being
assigned the post of honor, placed himself over against the punchbowl, and
between the high priest and his majesty the king, Quequ's father. Grace being
said, for those people have grace as well as we, though Quiquake told me that
unlike us, who at such times look downward to our platters, they, on the
contrary, copying the ducks, glance upward to the great giver of all feasts.
Grace, I say, being said, the high priest opens the banquet by the
immemorial ceremony of the island, that is, dipping his consecrated and
consecrating fingers into the bowl before the blessed beverage circulates.
seeing himself placed next to the priest and noting the ceremony and thinking
himself being captain of a ship as having plain precedence over a mere
island king, especially in the king's own house. The captain coolly proceeds
to wash his hands in the punch bowl, taking it, I suppose, for a huge finger
glass. Now, saidwiqu you think now?
Didn't our people laugh? At last passage paid and luggage safe, we stood on board
the schooner. Hoisting sail, it glided down the accashnet river. On one side
New Bedford rose in terraces of streets, their ice covered trees all glittering
in the clear cold air. Huge hills and mountains of casks on casks were piled
upon her warves, and side by side the whirl wandering whale ships lay silent
and safely mored at last, while from others came a sound of carpenters and
coopers with blended noises of fires and forges to melt the pitch, all betoening
that new cruises were on the start. that one most perilous and long voyage ended
only begins a second and a second ended only begins a third and so on forever
and for I such as the endlessness yay the intolerableness of all earthly
effort gaining the more open water the bracing breeze waxed fresh the little
moss tossed the quick foam from her boughs as a young cold his snortings how
I snuffed that tartar air how I spurned that turnpike earth that common highway
way, all over dented with the marks of slavish heels and hoofs, and turned me
to admire the magnanmity of the sea, which will permit no records.
At the same foam fountain, Quiquake seemed to drink and reel with me. His
dusky nostrils swelled apart. He showed his filed and pointed teeth. On, on we
flew, and our offing gained. The moss did homage to the blast. Ducked and
dived her boughs as a slave before the sultan. Sideways leaning, we sideways
darted. Every rope yarn tingling like a wire, the two tall mass buckling like
Indian canes in land tornadoes.
So full of this reeling scene were we, as we stood by the plunging bowsprit,
that for some time we did not notice the jeering glances of the passengers, a
lubberlike assembly, who marveled the two fellow being should be so
companionable, as though a white man were anything more dignified than a
whitewashed negro. But there were some boobies and bumpkins there, who, by
their intense greenness, must have come from the heart and center of all virquese
young saplings mimicking him behind his back. I thought the bumpkin's hour of
doom was come, dropping his harpoon, the brrawy savage caught him in his arms,
and by an almost miraculous dexterity and strength, sent him high up bodily
into the air. Then slightly tapping his stern in Midsomerset, the fellow landed
with bursting lungs upon his feet, while Quiquake, turning his back upon him,
lighted his tomahawk pipe, and passed it to me for a puff. "Captain! Captain!"
yelled the bumpkin, running towards that officer. "Captain! Captain, here's the
devil." "Hello, you, sir," cried the captain, a gaunt rib of the sea,
stalking up to Que. What in thunder do you mean by that? Don't you know you
might have killed that chap?
What him say? said Quiquake as he mildly turned to me. He say, said I, that you
came near Killy, that man there, pointing to the still shivering greenhorn.
Killy? Cried Quequ, twisting his tattooed face into an unearly expression
of disdain. Ah, him bevy. Small fishy.
Quiquake. No killy so smally fishy.
Quagilly big whale.
Look you, roared the captain. I'll killy you, you cannibal, if you try any more
of your tricks aboard here, so mind your eye. But it so happened just then that
it was high time for the captain to mind his own eye. The prodigious strain upon
the main sail had parted the weather sheet, and the tremendous boom was now
flying from side to side, completely sweeping the entire after part of the
deck. The poor fellow whom Quequake had handled so roughly was swept overboard.
All hands were in a panic, and to attempt snatching at the boom to stay it
seemed madness. It flew from right to left and back again, almost in one
ticking of a watch, and every instant seemed on the point of snapping into
splinters. Nothing was done, and nothing seemed capable of being done. Those on
deck rushed toward the boughs and stood eyeing the boom as if it were the lower
jaw of an exasperated whale. In the midst of this consternation, Quiquake
dropped deafly to his knees, and crawling under the path of the boom,
whipped hold of a rope, secured one end to the bull works, and then, flinging
the other like a lasso, caught it round the boom, as it swept over his head, and
at the next jerk the spar was that way trapped, and all was safe. The schooner
was run into the wind, and while the hands were clearing away the sternboat,
Quiqu stripped to the waist, darted from the side with a long living arc of a
leap. For 3 minutes or more he was seen swimming like a dog, throwing his long
arms straight out before him, and by turns revealing his brrawy shoulders
through the freezing foam. I looked at the grand and glorious fellow, but saw
no one to be saved. The greenhorn had gone down. Shooting himself
perpendicularly from the water, Quiquake now took an instant glance around him,
and seeming to see just how matters were, dived down and disappeared. A few
minutes more and he rose again, one arm still striking out, and with the other
dragging a lifeless form. The boat soon picked them up. The poor Bumpkin was
restored. All hands voted Quiquake and noble Trump, the captain begged his
pardon. From that hour I cloved to Que like a barnacle. Yay! Till poor
Quiquague took his last long dive.
Was there ever such unconsciousness? He did not seem to think that he at all
deserved a medal from the humane and magnanimous societies. He only asked for
water, fresh water, something to wipe the brine off. That done, he put on dry
clothes, lighted his pipe, and leaning against the bowl works, and mildly
eyeing those around him, seemed to be saying to himself, "It's a mutual joint
stock world in all meridians. We cannibals must help these Christians."